Finding Aid for the Lejaren Hiller Collection of Audio Tape Recordings, 1958-1985
State University of New York at Buffalo. Music Library
Lejaren Hiller Collection of Audio Tape Recordings, 1958-1985
Mus. Arc. 5.2
Hiller, Lejaren, 1924-1994
290 reel to reel tapes, 25 linear feet
State University of New York at Buffalo. Music Library
The collection contains Lejaren Hiller's personal collections of reel to reel tapes pertaining to his compositional output. It includes recordings of live performances of works as well as recordings of some of the electronic source materials used in other compositions.
Administrative Information
Terms of Access
Materials can be examined by qualified researchers in the Music Library during hours of operation during which Music Librarians are present. In order to insure access, researchers are advised to contact the Music Library in advance of visits.
Alternate Forms
Two hundred twenty three tapes have been digitally reformatted by George Blood Audio using funds from The New York State Program for the Conservation and Preservation of Library Research Materials - Coordinated Aid Program. The container list includes indications of which tapes were reformatted.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Elizabeth Hiller.
Accruals and Additions
No further accruals are expected to this collection.
Biographical Note
Lejaren Hiller was born on February 23, 1924, in New York City. He received his B.A., M.A., and Ph.D. in chemistry from Princeton University, where he also studied music theory and composition with Milton Babbitt and Roger Sessions. In 1958, Hiller received his M. Mus. from the University of Illinois where he founded the Experimental Music Studio.
In 1957, Hiller collaborated with Leonard Isaacson on the Illiac Suite, the first significant use of a computer in composition. The Illiac Suite (String Quartet No. 4) was so named for the Illiac computer on which the calculations for the score parameters were made. Hiller was able to tap the power of the Illiac for the generation and selection of large quantities of random values in a fundamental type of stochastic modeling known as "the Monte Carlo Method."
Lejaren Hiller's importance to the field of computer music cannot be over-emphasized. His work on the use of computers for the generation of musical parameters such as pitch, rhythm, duration, etc. in pieces of music using traditional instruments, opened a door to new methods of music material generation and simultaneously to the computer-assisted analysis of the process of music composition.
Scope and Content Note
The collection contains Lejaren Hiller's personal collections of reel to reel tapes pertaining to his compositional output. It includes recordings of live performances of works as well as recordings of some of the electronic source materials used in other compositions.
Seventy-two of Hiller's compositions, out of an approximate total of eighty works, are included in the collection. Almost all of the recorded performances in the collection took place under Hiller's direction, or in his presence. They represent a historical record of his performance preferences and possibly contain critical information about performance practices of the period. The tapes for Hiller's electronic music compositions are unique to this collection. Multiple tapes exist for many of the compositions that combine electronic and acoustic sound sources. One tape may contain the electronic cues for a work and another tape an entire performance of the work. There are also multiple tapes of electronic sound sources for those of Hiller's compositions that are entirely electronic.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in one series chiefly by the Hiller work number of the first work on the tape. Tapes with collections and Hiller's teaching materials are at the end of the collection.
Container List
- Hiller, Lejaren, 1924-1994 Sonata no. 1 for piano (1946, revised 1968) (H. 1), Recorded July 10, 1975, 1 7 inch reel; 7 ½ ips, 2-channel stereo.; Duplicate of Tape 2 Performers: Kenwyn Boldt, piano Duration: 28:15 Tape digitally reformatted: No (Item 001)
  I. Molto Moderato, Andante, Vivace, Allegro, etc. 9:50 II. Prestissimo 1:21 III. Adagio 7:37 IV. Allegro Grazioso 8:15 +0:12
- Hiller, Lejaren, 1924-1994 Sonata no. 1 for piano (1946, revised 1968) (H. 1), Recorded live at concert, July 10, 1975, 1 10 inch reel; 15 ips, 2-channel stereo., Dolby A301 stretched; Master tape Performers: Kenwyn Boldt, piano Duration: 28:15 Tape digitally reformatted: Yes (Item 002)
- Hiller, Lejaren, 1924-1994 Sonata no. 2 for piano (1947) (H. 2), undated, 1 7 inch reel; speed unknown; Duplicate of Tape 4 Performers: Charles Clifton, piano Duration: 21:31 Tape digitally reformatted: No (Item 003)
  I. Allegro Appassionato 10:31 II. Tango 4:22 III. Scherzo (Allegro Vivace) 6:56 +0:12
- Hiller, Lejaren, 1924-1994 Sonata no. 2 for piano (1947) (H. 2), Recorded May and June 1980, 1 10 inch reel; 15 ips, 2-channel stereo., Dolby A noise reduction; Master tape Performers: Charles Clifton, piano Duration: 21:17 Tape digitally reformatted: Yes (Item 004)
  I. Sonata Allegro: Allegro Appassionato 9:47 II. Tango: Andante 4:22 III. Scherzo: Allegro Vivace, Cantabile, Allegro Vivace, Cantabile, Allegro Vivace 6:56 +0:12
- Hiller, Lejaren, 1924-1994 Trio for violin, cello and piano (1947) (H. 3), Recorded November 19, 1976, 1 7 inch reel; 7 ½ ips, 2-channel stereo.; Duplicate of Tape 6 Performers: Keiko Yamazaki, violin; Bonnie Black, violoncello; Charles Clifton, piano Duration: 28:10 Tape digitally reformatted: No (Item 005)
  I. Allegro Moderato 8:25 II. Allegro Brutale (Scherzo); Andantino con Vino (Trio) 5:07 III. Adagio (Intermezzo) 7:08 IV. Allegro Vivace, Presto 7:18 +0:12
- Hiller, Lejaren, 1924-1994 Trio for violin, cello and piano (1947) (H. 3), Recorded November 19, 1976, 1 10 inch reel; 15 ips, 2-channel stereo.; Master tape Performers: Keiko Yamazaki, violin; Bonnie Black, violoncello; Charles Clifton, piano Duration: 28:08 Tape digitally reformatted: Yes (Item 006)
  I. Allegro Moderato 8:25 II. Allegro Brutale (Scherzo); Andantino con Vino (Trio) 5:07 III. Adagio (Intermezzo) 7:08 IV. Allegro Vivace, Presto 7:18 +0:10
- Hiller, Lejaren, 1924-1994 Seven artifacts, for piano (1948, revised 1973). Selections (H. 4), Recorded May 4, 1982, 1 5 inch reel; 7 ½ ips, 2-channel stereo., Tail out; Unique performance Performers: Nils Vigeland, piano Tape digitally reformatted: Yes (Item 007)
  1. [No. 6] Blue Triangle; 2. [No. 7] Ormolu
- Hiller, Lejaren, 1924-1994 Seven artifacts, for piano (1948, revised 1973) (H. 4), undated, 1 7 inch reel; speed unknown, 2-channel stereo.; Unique performance Performers: Frina Boldt (1,4), Szablocz Esztenyi (2,3,5), Nils Vigeland (7), Yvar Mikhashoff (6) Duration: 27:34 Tape digitally reformatted: Yes (Item 008)
  I. String of Pearls 5:10 II. Palindrome 3:20 III. Plinth 5:05 IV. Filigree 3:56 V. Clockwork 2:52 VI. Blue Triangle 3:52 VII. Ormolu 3:21
- Hiller, Lejaren, 1924-1994 Seven artifacts, for piano (1948, revised 1973) (H. 4), Recorded December 14, 1983, 1 7 inch reel; speed unknown; Duplicate of Tape 10 Performers: Naomi Weinfeld, piano Duration: 29:46 Tape digitally reformatted: No (Item 009)
  I. String of Pearls 5:41 II. Palindrome 3:18 III. Plinth 5:55 IV. Filigree 4:24 V. Clockwork 3:32 VI. Blue Triangle 3:09 VII. Ormolu 3:23 +0:24
- Hiller, Lejaren, 1924-1994 Seven artifacts, for piano (1948, revised 1973) (H. 4), Recorded December 14, 1983, 1 10 inch reel; 15 ips, 2-channel stereo., Dolby A, Tail out; Master tape Performers: Naomi Weinfeld, piano Duration: 29:46 Tape digitally reformatted: Yes (Item 010)
- Hiller, Lejaren, 1924-1994 Seven artifacts, for piano (1948, revised 1973) (H. 4), 1st work recorded July 10, 1974 (1,4) and December 10, 1973 (Warsaw)(2,3,5,6); 2nd work recorded in concert, 1 10 inch reel; 7 ½ and 15 ips (Movements 1 and 4 of Seven Artifacts), 2-channel stereo., Movements 1 and 4 of Seven Artifacts recorded with Dolby; Storage Possible duplication but with unique performances, too Performers: 1st work performed by Frina Boldt (1,4), Szablocz Esztenyi (2,3,5,6), and Nils Vigeland (7); 2nd work performed by Randall Kramer, piano Duration: 14:00 (Children's Suite) Tape digitally reformatted: Yes (Item 011)
  I. String of Pearls II. Palindrome III. Plinth IV. Filigree V. Clockwork VI. Blue Triangle VII. Ormolu
  Additional content:
  H. 8, Children's Suite for piano (1949) I. Prelude II. Country Dance III. Processional IV. Pastorale V. Minuet VI. Romance VII. Finale 14:00
- Hiller, Lejaren, 1924-1994 String quartet No. 1 (1949) (H. 5), Recorded October 9, 1977, 1 7 inch reel; speed unknown; Unless Tape 13 is in superior condition Performers: Kronos String Quartet Duration: Part One: 18:21; Part Two: 18:58; Total 37:25 First complete performance Tape digitally reformatted: Yes (Item 012)
  Part One: I. Allegro 7:08 II. Allegro Moderato, etc. (Scherzo) 7:10 III. Allegretto 4:03 Spacer 0:06 Part Two: IV. Adagio 10:39 V. Allegro Risoluto (Fugue) 5:21 VI. Presto (Epilog)
- Hiller, Lejaren, 1924-1994 String quartet No. 1 (1949) (H. 5), undated, 1 10 inch reel; 7 ½ ips, 2-channel stereo., Tail out; Storage tapes Duplicate storage tape of Tapes 12 and Tape 68; Use this tape if those tapes are in worse condition Performers: 1st work performed by the Kronos String Quartet; 2nd work performed by the Concord String Quartet Tape digitally reformatted: No (Item 013)
  H. 31, String quartet No. 5 (1961)
- Hiller, Lejaren, 1924-1994 Sonata, No. 1 for violin and piano (1949) (H. 7), undated, 1 7 inch reel; speed unknown; No Master tape identified for Sonata; Master tape for H. 10 is Tape 21 - use that instead? Performers: 1st work performed by Thomas Halpin, violin, and Yvar Mikhashoff, piano; 2nd work performed by Jane Bane, Marjorie Rosenberg, Keith Daniel, Andrew Schultze, and Jane Cary, piano Duration: 19:58 (Sonata No. 1); 7:54 (Jesse James) Tape digitally reformatted: Yes (Item 014)
  I. Elegy (Andante) 9:23 II. Scherzo (Allegretto Pomposo) 3:33 III. Rondo (Allegro Moderato) 6:54 Spacers 0:08
  H. 10, Jesse James, for vocal quartet and piano (1950)
- Hiller, Lejaren, 1924-1994 Sonata, No. 1 for violin and piano (1949) (H. 7), undated, 1 10 inch reel; speed unknown; Storage tapes Probable storage duplicate of Tape 14 Sonata no. 1 Master tape of H. 18a is Tape 36 Master tape of H. 18b is Tape 36 Possible use if Tape 14 or Tape 36 in inferior condition Spine label only Tape digitally reformatted: No (Item 015)
  H. 18a, Sonata, No. 2 for violin and piano (1955)
  H. 18b Sonata for cello and piano (1955/77)
- Hiller, Lejaren, 1924-1994 Children's suite, for piano (1949) (H. 8), undated, 1 7 inch reel; speed unknown; Master tape is Tape 17 Performers: Frina Boldt, piano Duration: 18:00 (Children's suite); 13:35 (Sonata No. 3 for piano) Tape digitally reformatted: Yes (Item 016)
  I. Prelude II. Country Dance III. Processional IV. Pastorale V. Minuet VI. Romance VII. Finale
  H. 9, Sonata, No. 3 for piano (1950) I. Allegro Moderato II. Andantino III. Presto (Scherzo) IV. Allegro (Fugue)
- Hiller, Lejaren, 1924-1994 Children's suite, for piano (1949) (H. 8), undated, 1 10 inch reel; speed unknown; Master tape of Children's suite Master; although not stated, it is likely the same performance as Tape 16 Contains two copies of pieces 2, 3, 4, 6, and 7 Tape digitally reformatted: Yes (Item 017)
- Hiller, Lejaren, 1924-1994 Children's suite, for piano (1949) (H. 8), undated, 1 10 inch reel; speed unknown; Back up of some of the Children's suite Duplicate backup tape Tape digitally reformatted: No (Item 018)
- Hiller, Lejaren, 1924-1994 Sonata, No. 3 for piano (1950) (H. 9), undated, 1 10 inch reel; 15 ips, 2-channel stereo., Dolby A, Tail out; Master tape Master tape for H. 9 and H. 19; H. 19 master also on Tape 38 (different performance) Four early pieces not listed in works list Performers: 1st and 2nd work performed by Charles Clifton, piano; last work (Four Early Pieces) performed by Yvar Mikhashoff, piano Duration: 14:56 (Sonata No. 3 for piano); 3:34 (Two Theatre pieces for piano) Tape digitally reformatted: Yes (Item 019)
  I. Allegro 7:01 II. Andantino 3:43 III. Presto 2:19 IV. Allegro 1:35 Spacers 0:12
  H. 19, Two theater pieces, for piano (1956) I. Aria Spacers 0:04 II. Chords and Wild Dance 1:34 Four Early Pieces (1948/49) I. Prelude (from H. 8) II. Aria (from H. 19) III. Chords and Wild Dance (from H. 19) IV. Blue Triangle (from H. 4) Spacers 0:12
- Hiller, Lejaren, 1924-1994 Sonata, No. 3 for piano (1950) (H. 9), undated, 1 10 inch reel; speed unknown; Master tape and sub-master Master; no performer identified; duration differs from Tape 19 Duration: 13:35 (Master tape) Tape digitally reformatted: Yes (Item 020)
- Hiller, Lejaren, 1924-1994 Jesse James, for vocal quartet and piano (1950) (H. 10), 2nd work recorded July 7, 1973, 1 10 inch reel; 15 ips, 2-channel stereo., Dolby A301 stretched, Tail out (2nd work); Master tape Performers: 1st work performed by Jane Bane, Marjorie Rosenberg, Keith Daniel, Andrew Schultze (vocal quartet), and Jane Cary, piano; 2nd work performed by Winifred Black, soprano, and David Sussman, guitar. Duration: 25:39 total (7:54 and 17:39) Tape digitally reformatted: Yes (Item 021)
  H. 24, Five Appalachian ballads, for voice and guitar/harpsichord (1958) I. Lord Randal 3:36 II. Barbara Allen 4:06 III. The Three Ravens 1:12 IV. The Cruel Mother 5:16 V. The Two Sisters 3:13 Spacers 0:16
- Hiller, Lejaren, 1924-1994 Sonata, No. 4 for piano (1950) (H. 11), undated, 1 7 inch reel; 7 ½ ips, 2-channel stereo.; Duplicate of Master tape 23 Performers: Frina Boldt, piano Duration: 29:20 Tape digitally reformatted: No (Item 022)
  I. Andante; Allegro Vivace 12:04 II. Andante con Moto; Allegretto Vivace 7:20 III. Alla Marcia; Allegretto Serioso 5:56 IV. Prestissimo 3:48 Spacers 0:12
- Hiller, Lejaren, 1924-1994 Sonata, No. 4 for piano (1950) (H. 11), Recorded June 1970, 1 10 inch reel; 15 ips, 2-channel stereo., Dolby A; Dolby A301 stretched, Tail out; Master tape Performers: Frina Boldt, piano Duration: 29:20 Tape digitally reformatted: Yes (Item 023)
- Hiller, Lejaren, 1924-1994 String quartet No. 2 (1951) (H. 13), undated, 1 7 inch reel; speed unknown; Duplicate of Tape 25 Performers: Pro Arte Zagreb String Quartet Duration: 27:51 Tape digitally reformatted: No (Item 024)
  I. Adagio 14:50 II. Allegro 12:57 Spacer 0:04
- Hiller, Lejaren, 1924-1994 String quartet No. 2 (1951) (H. 13), undated, 1 10 inch reel; 15 ips, 2-channel stereo.; Master tape Master, "without editing" Performers: Pro Arte Zagreb String Quartet Duration: 27:51 Without editing as on 7 ½ storage tape of 2nd movement Tape digitally reformatted: Yes (Item 025)
  I. Adagio 14:50* II. Allegro 12:57 0:04 * including estimate for missing bars
- Hiller, Lejaren, 1924-1994 String quartet No. 2 (1951) (H. 13), Recorded 1974, 1 10 inch reel; 15 ips, 2-channel stereo.; Sub-master "properly edited sub-master tape (follows formal edition of score). Performers: Zagreb Pro Arte String Quartet Duration: 27:40 Properly edited sub-master tape (follows formal edition of score) Tape digitally reformatted: Yes (Item 026)
  I. Adagio 14:36 II. Allegro 13:00 Spacer 0:04
- Hiller, Lejaren, 1924-1994 Fantasy, for three pianos (1951) (H. 14), Recorded June 1983, 1 7 inch reel; 7 ½ ips, 2-channel stereo.; Duplicate on Master tape 28 Performers: Stephen Manes, Frieda Manes, Yvar Mikhashoff Duration: 16:54 Tape digitally reformatted: No (Item 027)
- Hiller, Lejaren, 1924-1994 Fantasy, for three pianos (1951) (H. 14), undated, 1 10 inch reel; 15 ips, 2-channel stereo., Dolby A, Tail out; Master tape Master; possibly unique performances of accompanying works Performers: 1st work performed by Stephen Manes, Frieda Manes, and Yvar Mikhashoff; other works performed by Yvar Mikhashoff Duration: 24:50 total (16:41 Fantasy) Tape digitally reformatted: Yes (Item 028)
  Additional content: Four short pieces
  I. Prelude from “Children’s Suite” (H. 8) 1:16 Spacer 0:04
  II. Two Theater Pieces (1) Aria from Pirandello’s “Right You Are” (H. 19) 2:53 Spacer 0:04
  III. Two Theater Pieces (2) “Wild Dance For Ibsen’s “Hedda Gabler” (H.19) 0:53 Spacer 0:04
  IV. Seven Artifacts #6 Blue Triangle (H. 4) 2:48
- Hiller, Lejaren, 1924-1994 Fantasy, for three pianos (1951) (H. 14), undated, 1 10 inch reel; 15 ips, 2-channel stereo., Dolby A, Tail out; Master tape Master; duplicate of H. 46 on Tape 137 Performers: 1st work performed by Stephen Manes, Frieda Manes, and Yvar Mikhashoff; 2nd work performed by Kenwyn Boldt and Frina Boldt Duration: 16:43 (Fantasy); 17:37 (Cenotaph) Tape digitally reformatted: Yes (Item 029)
  H. 46, A cenotaph, for two pianos (1971)
- Hiller, Lejaren, 1924-1994 String quartet No. 3 (1953) (H. 16), Recorded March 24, 1976, 1 7 inch reel; 7 ½ ips, 2-channel stereo.; Different performance date from Tape 31 and 32 Performers: Kronos String Quartet Duration: 24:00 Tape digitally reformatted: Yes (Item 030)
  I. Allegro Con brio 6:16 II. Lento, ma non troppo 5:44 III. Scherzo- allegro energico, Trio-Vivace 4:52 IV. Presto 6:54 Spacers 0:12
- Hiller, Lejaren, 1924-1994 String quartet No. 3 (1953) (H. 16), Recorded June 27, 1981, 1 10 inch reel; 15 ips, 2-channel stereo., Dolby A; Master tape Master; unique performance date Performers: Kronos String Quartet Duration: 24:44 Tape digitally reformatted: Yes (Item 031)
- Hiller, Lejaren, 1924-1994 String quartet No. 3 (1953) (H. 16), Recorded June 28, 1981, 1 10 inch reel; 15 ips, 2-channel stereo., Dolby A; Submaster Submaster; unique performance date Performers: Kronos String Quartet Duration: 24:18 Tape digitally reformatted: Yes (Item 032)
- Hiller, Lejaren, 1924-1994 Twelve-tone variations, for piano (1954) (H. 17), Recorded October 1971, 1 7 inch reel; 7 ½ ips, 2-channel stereo.; Different recording date from Master Tape 34 Performers: Roger Shields, piano Duration: 30:49 Tape digitally reformatted: Yes (Item 033)
  I. Theme (on Six Tone Rows) II. Variations on Individual Tone Rows III. Variations on Pairs of Tone Rows IV. Variations on Three Tone Rows V. Variations on Four and Six Tone Rows
- Hiller, Lejaren, 1924-1994 Twelve-tone variations, for piano (1954) (H. 17), Recorded Spring 1971, 1 10 inch reel; 15 ips, 2-channel stereo, Dolby A stretched, Tail out; Master tape Master; different recording date from Tape 33 Performers: Roger Shields Duration: 30:33 Tape digitally reformatted: Yes (Item 034)
  I. Theme (Six Tone Rows Combined) 1:37 II. Variations on Individual Tone Rows 5:10 III. Variations on Pairs of Tone Rows 6:21 IV. Variations on Three Tone Rows 5:26 V. Variations on Four Tone Rows and Six Tone Rows 11:35
- Hiller, Lejaren, 1924-1994 Sonata, No. 2 for violin and piano (1955) (H. 18a), undated, 1 7 inch reel; speed unknown; Duplicate of Master tape 36 Performers: 1st work performed by Thomas Halpin, Violin, and Yvar Mikhashoff, piano; 2nd work performed by Frances-Marie Uitti, violoncello, and Yvar Mikhashoff, piano. Duration: 19:06 (1st work); 18:04 (2nd work) Tape digitally reformatted: No (Item 035)
  I. Allegro 8:38 II. Larghetto 4:24 III. Allegro Molto Vivace 5:56
  H. 18b, Sonata for cello and piano (1955/77) (Incomplete) I. Allegro II. Larghetto III. Allegro Molto Vivace
- Hiller, Lejaren, 1924-1994 Sonata, No. 2 for violin and piano (1955) (H. 18a), undated, 1 10 inch reel; 15 ips, 2-channel stereo., Dolby A, Tail out; Master tape Duration: 19:06 (1st work); 18:04 (2nd work) Tape digitally reformatted: Yes (Item 036)
  I. Allegro 8:38 II. Larghetto 4:24 III. Allegro Molto Vivace 5:56 Spacers 0:08
  H. 18b, Sonata for cello and piano (1955/77) I. Allegro 8:26 II. Larghetto 4:22 III. Allegro Molto Vivace 5:08 Spacers 0:08
- Hiller, Lejaren, 1924-1994 Two theater pieces, for piano (1956) (H. 19), 2nd work recorded 1964, 1 7 inch reel; speed unknown; Possibly unique recording of H. 23 (see Tape 43 for other performance) Performers: 1st work performed by Yvar Mikhashoff; 2nd work performed by Arthur Maddox Duration: 3:48 (1st work); 15:06 (2nd work) Tape digitally reformatted: Yes (Item 037)
  I. Aria II. Chords and Wild Dance
  H. 23, Scherzo, for piano (1958)
- Hiller, Lejaren, 1924-1994 Two theater pieces, for piano (1956) Plus “Prelude” from Children’s Suite (H. 8) and “Blue Triangle From “Seven Artifacts” (H. 4) (H. 19), Illiac Suite recorded January 1967, 1 10 inch reel; 15 ips, 2-channel stereo, Dolby A301 stretched, Tail out; Master tape (Two Theater Pieces); Master Tape for Disk Recording (Illiac Suite) Performers: Illiac Suite performed by the University of Illinois Composition String Quartet; Two Theater Pieces performed by Yvar Mikhashoff Duration: 18:20 (Illiac Suite); 8:06 (Two Theater Pieces) H. 20, String quartet No. 4, "Illiac suite" (1957) composed with Leonard Isaacson Tape digitally reformatted: Yes (Item 038)
  H. 20, String quartet No. 4, "Illiac suite" (1957) I. Experiment 1 4:38 II. Experiment 2 4:01 III. Experiment 3 5:59 IV. Experiment 4 3:29
- Hiller, Lejaren, 1924-1994 String quartet No. 4, "Illiac suite" (1957), composed with Leonard Isaacson (H. 20), undated, 1 7 inch reel; speed unknown; Movement headings for H. 20 differ from Tape 38 but durations are same and it is presumed to be same performance Performers: University of Illinois Composition String Quartet Duration: 18:19 Tape digitally reformatted: No (Item 039)
  I. Presto; Andante; Allegro 4:38 II. Adagio, ma non Troppo 4:01 III. Allegro con Brio 5:59 IV. Tanto Presto che Possibile 3:29 0:12
- Hiller, Lejaren, 1924-1994 Music for "A dream play", by August Strindberg (1957) (H. 21), undated, 1 7 inch reel; 7 ½ ips, Dual mono.; Duplicate of Submaster Tape 41 Performers: Performed by a Chamber Ensemble, conducted by Lejaren Hiller Tape digitally reformatted: No (Item 040)
  Side One: Act I; Act II (beginning) Side Two: Act II (concluded)
- Hiller, Lejaren, 1924-1994 Music for "A dream play", by August Strindberg (1957) (H. 21), undated, 1 10 inch reel; 7 ½ ips, full-track mono.; Submaster Submaster Performers: Ensemble conducted by Lejaren Hiller Original master discarded Tape digitally reformatted: Yes (Item 041)
- Hiller, Lejaren, 1924-1994 Music for "The birds", by Aristophanes as adapted by Walter Kerr (1958) (H. 22), undated, 1 7 inch reel; 7 ½ ips; Duplicate of Master tape 43 Performers: "Theater Orchestra conducted by Lejaren Hiller (new insertions conducted by Steven Swarz)." Duration: 38:08 Tape digitally reformatted: No (Item 042)
  Act I 27:41 Act II 10:21 0:06
- Hiller, Lejaren, 1924-1994 Music for "The birds", by Aristophanes as adapted by Walter Kerr (1958) (H. 22), undated, 1 10 inch reel; 7 ½ ips, full-track mono., Tail out; Master tape Performers: Ensembles conducted by Lejaren Hiller or Steven Swarz Tape digitally reformatted: Yes (Item 043)
- Hiller, Lejaren, 1924-1994 Five Appalachian ballads, for voice and guitar/harpsichord (1958) (H. 24), undated, 1 7 inch reel; speed unknown; Possibly unique performances Performers: Version 1 is performed by Winifred Black, soprano, and David Sussman, guitar; Version 2 is performed by Martha Herr, soprano, and Yvar Mikhashoff, piano. Duration: 16:28 (Version 1); 16:39 (Version 2) Version 1: For Voice and Guitar; Version 2: For Voice and Piano Tape digitally reformatted: Yes (Item 044)
  I. Lord Randal II. Barbara Allen III. Three Old Crows IV. The Cruel Mother V. The Two Sisters
- Hiller, Lejaren, 1924-1994 Five Appalachian ballads, for voice and guitar/harpsichord (1958) (H. 24), undated, 1 7 inch reel; 7 ½ ips, mono., Head out,; Possibly unique performances Performers: H. 24 performed by Phyllis Hurt and Roger Shields; H. 27 performed by Elizabeth Hiller; H. 40 performed by Royal MacDonald (speaker), Norma Marder (soprano), and Robert Rosen (percussion) Duration: 15:00 (H. 24); 2:30 (H. 27); 10:00 (H. 40) Tape digitally reformatted: Yes (Item 045)